<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Caro-carita. A treatise discovering the true nature of charity: how far consistent with our own primary inherency: and how nighly paralell'd in vulgar practice. / Composed by L.W.</title>
            <author>L. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W78</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1716_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209653</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868518</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868518</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170303</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97132)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170303)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 213:E1716[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Caro-carita. A treatise discovering the true nature of charity: how far consistent with our own primary inherency: and how nighly paralell'd in vulgar practice. / Composed by L.W.</title>
                  <author>L. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 90, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for Stephen and Thomas Lewis, and are to be sold at their shop, at the signe of the Book-binders in Shoe-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658 [i.e. 1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy Dec. 19 1657.</note>
                  <note>With a final leaf of errata.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec 19"; also the last number of the imprint date has been marked through and replaced with a "7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170303:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Caro-Carīta.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the true Nature of CHARITY: How far conſiſtent with our own prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Inherency: And how nighly para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell'd in vulgar Practice.</p>
            <p>Compoſed by <hi>L. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for <hi>Stephen</hi> and <hi>Thomas Lewis,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop, at the ſigne of the <hi>Book-binders</hi> in <hi>Shoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170303:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170303:2"/>
            <head>TO THE moſt Worthily Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lady Theodoſialvie</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned this Treatiſe for the Inſtruction of a Minde yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable; leaſt Errour or Malice ſhould under ſuch la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb facs="tcp:170303:3"/>of Time intercept the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; I have preſumed to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore hereto the Influence of your Graces; That the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of your Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes might warrant it a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure tutelage to
<pb facs="tcp:170303:3"/>Poſterity. The Nature of the Subject will, I hope, ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully intercede for your Rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption; ſince it is the perfect Character of your own pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall Piety: and the faireſt Pledge to your
<pb facs="tcp:170303:4"/>celeſtiall Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency. (Nor can the Aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſſe for ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Ceremony) the living Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of your Glory are as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and the Conſequence as
<pb facs="tcp:170303:4"/>effectuall as a continuall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, regemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of gratefull Votaries. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, both Civill and Intellectuall Endowments, have in your fruition thereof, attained the
<pb facs="tcp:170303:5"/>higheſt Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, fully meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the due In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of their Enlargement, their unintereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed diſtribution. All Arts and Sciences what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever have faln from their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Honour, Credit, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſibly
<pb facs="tcp:170303:5"/>their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy, ſince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Objects of Commerce and Proſtitutes to abject Lucre. The ſplendor of their glory ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives yet onely in your Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of their Virtues. The Influence of
<pb facs="tcp:170303:6"/>whoſe miniſtry therein, extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beyond the pretence of any Relation or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. It being to any an irreſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible Plea to a, Right in your ſuccour, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that they want it. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb facs="tcp:170303:6"/>an impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in which poſition I muſt not ſo far treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs againſt the Dignity of ſo communicable a Bounty, as indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt thereof to thruſt theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes into a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular exception. Nor will the
<pb facs="tcp:170303:7"/>rules of Civility admit thereto ſo confident an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction, as to precede the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Election: I will therefore humbly waite your pleaſure to diſtinguiſh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what degree of Inherency you
<pb facs="tcp:170303:7"/>ſhall vouchſafe to ſhelter this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, tendered <hi>by,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your humbly devoted Servant, <hi>L. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170303:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170303:8"/>
            <head>Caro-Carīta</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sonne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the moſt perfect Method to form exactly our own Judgement is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically to inform anothers; and that the moſt legitimate Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority can admit us to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170303:9"/>the priviledge of this practice, is what Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath conſtituted on us in the production of our kinde; I have long ſince (in regard our fraile compoſure can ſcarce promiſe to us a rationall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication betwixt gray hairs and the Cradle) formed a purpoſe in my Intention, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for thee a Tract of Natural, Civill, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Notions, as the moſt proper and uſeful ſubjects of Inſtruction, ſolely conducing to the improvement of our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170303:9"/>beeing; whereby thou mayeſt facily and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attain to that capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as to avoid thoſe ſhelves, thy faithfull Pilot ſhall diſcover to thee, by the wrack of his own fame and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes (inſeparable co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents) yet in reſpect no time falleth within the diſpenſation of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent I am forced to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Order of my Deſigne; commencing with that principall, ſhould crown the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our enterpriſe: and ſince we cannot
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170303:10"/>hope to reach a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to treat of All; at leaſt to diſcuſs of the moſt Neceſſary.</p>
            <p>In reference to which, the higheſt Principall in Practicall Divinity being <hi>Charity.</hi> The utmoſt Object, to which every progreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Religion tendeth <hi>Scala vel ad ſummum at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet uſque polum;</hi> from whoſe implicite opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is derived her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite denomination, <hi>Religare, to binde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether;</hi> a compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous modell of the whol Law: and without
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170303:10"/>which, <hi>The tongues of men and Angels, with the higheſt and moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full operations or illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the ſpirit, or what other celeſtiall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſo ever are but as tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckling Cymbals, or as ſounding Braſſe.</hi> This being an indiſputable Axiome in this high myſtery; it will be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially important tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſtinguiſh of her Nature, leaſt we reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on ſome imperfect ſimilitude thereof, ſhould deviate from this glorious light, and by ſuch empty exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170303:11"/>be ſeduced to our ruine; eſpecially, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the raviſhing lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of her graces de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow'red in the propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of her Attribute, under a proverbiall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certion, <hi>Charity begins at home.</hi> A Vulgar po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, wanting neither the Approbation nor Practice of the graveſt, wiſeſt and moſt Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in repute to lend it a more warrantable au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. But to remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate unto thee, how repugnant this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in the order of her objects, is to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170303:11"/>nature of her Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; leaſt the Devill ſhould deceive thee under the figure of an Angel of light, we will endeavour to diſcover the errour of this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net.</p>
            <p>Methodically pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, firſt, perfectly to delineate the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſubject of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in a full &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous Definition: To which true original tracing any parrallel, we clearly may diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the ſimilitude or diſſimilitude in the particulars. In purſuit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170303:12"/>of which Rule, we muſt acknowledge <hi>Charity to be a free act of the Will to relieve another, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from no other conſideration, end, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, whatſoever, than the compaſſionate ſenſe of anothers ſuffering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The qualification of the act, though ſimple may properly extend to a triple expoſition in her nature, free in reſpect of the motive of the act; free in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the manner of the act; free in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the meaſure thereof.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170303:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the Motive free, not indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by impulſion, as importunity or Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; Aſſent attained by the one, viſeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly but at our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per quiet; by the other, but obliquely to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Interceſſors: Nor by Impoſition, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a legall Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, civill Rule, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Order: Munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in conformity to the firſt, can be qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but Obedience; to the ſecond but Gratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; to the third, but an innate Retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170303:13"/>2. Free in reſpect of the manner, without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting, grudging, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching, or inſulting.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Protraction incurs the hazzards of that guilt, may probably enſue, in the doubtfull miſcarriage of another: while the ſuſpended will in the affected de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, betrayeth in it ſelf an indifference to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally inconſiſtent with the nature of ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a Conſequence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Grudging implies a retraction of the will, which defaceth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Acts ere it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170303:13"/>is fully formed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reproaching in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates a contradiction in the nature of the Motive, figuring at once, both a prope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion and an Averſion, twins following ſo cloſe in iſſue, that the younger ſeems to ſupplant the elder, whilſt one pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Oyl in the wound, the other ſeeks to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large it by Inciſion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Inſulting pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims rather a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Acquiſition to our ſelves, than of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption to another; whileſt one hand hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170303:14"/>ſtoops to unlooſe the Shekle at the foot, the other arrogantly preſumes to caſt the yoke about the neck.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Free in regard of the Meaſure: this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction extends it ſelf firſt to the Capacity of the Agent, next to the Exigence of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient. As he that hath to the utmoſt of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty miniſtred to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Neceſſity, though not ſupplied, the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency hath attained the merit of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking. So he that hath liberally advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170303:14"/>the welfare of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a timely ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, yet reſtrained his hand, by the reluctance onely of his will, from finiſhing his reſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, abandoning the diſtreſſed to the former hazzard of his Ruine, hath totally forfeited the Glory of his Incep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; if not rendred himſelf guilty of the future iſſue: The true Object of <hi>Charity,</hi> being to redeem another from Affliction, not to prolong anothers miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>The generall Object
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170303:15"/>of this celeſtial vertue, Relief, extends to as vaſt a latitude as our fraile Natures are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to caſualties or defects, whereto it is appropriated, <hi>She</hi> is a guide to the blinde; a ſupport to the Lame; food to the Hungry; raiment to the Naked, and counſel to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that if we ſhall truly conſider Her in her proper Nature; no one can be found ſo happy, which may not, nay, which doth not become the Subject of her Miniſtry: Nor no
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170303:15"/>one ſo wretched, which may not become Her Miniſter: ſo full a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Parts is in our Civill compoſition to grace that Harmony might iſſue from the Agreement of our mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Love.</p>
            <p>The Subject or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of this officious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, is only the <hi>compaſſionate ſenſe of anothers Miſery.</hi> How far ſuch reflective par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of anothers evill may be conſiſtent with that rigid tenure of Philoſophy, which ſtruggleth onely to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170303:16"/>ſupport the mind im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, placing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation of the Soule rather in magnanimity than Indulgency; in Greatneſſe more than Goodneſſe: may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly require a vaſter Agitation, than will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the Simetry of our preſent Treatiſe. Yet thus much we may briefly infer in confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our Poſition, That the regular Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſenſe are as neceſſary to the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſouls Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: as is a gale of Winde to the progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170303:16"/>of a Bark upon the ſurface of the Ocean: without which it can neither be Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative to it ſelf or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; the nobleſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of every moral virtue; unleſs we ſhould improperly admit, this Speculation to purſue an Object diſtinct from her Nature whereof it but pretends to be the originall: a ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on inconſiſtent with the very Eſſence of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual graces, which are ſo viſibly united in coherence of Effects, as they but form one only
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170303:17"/>Nature: Nor can there be a communicative fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, without the ſenſe of an impulſive motive, which is expreſſed even in the Election, with more than an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall indifferency: Beſides which interior Compunction in the Motive, there muſt be alſo an interiour Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in the miniſtry to form the Excellence of <hi>this celeſtiall Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute.</hi> The debordments onely of ſuperfluity are not ſufficient pledges to merit the perfection of her dignity, though
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170303:17"/>iſſuing from the moſt perfect Sincerity. Slighter diſpenſations may ſometime poſſibly figure her Nature. But <hi>Seipſum vel ex ſeipſo ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid voluntarie perientis ſaluti contribuere, eſt quidem opus verè Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> To contribute voluntarily himſelf, or any thing from himſelf to the ſafety of a periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man: is queſtionleſs a work truly divine; as may appear by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and teſtimony of that incarnate <hi>Word,</hi> who formd her Nature. Nor yet can every Act of Benevolence receive
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170303:18"/>ſo high an Illuſtration, to be inveſted with the Ornaments of Her Title; The threatnings of a deſtructive exigent muſt meet our miniſtry to qualifie our aid with ſuch a Dignity: not that every degree of diſtreſſe, may not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume an equall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; if weighed in the Conſequence with ſuch an apprehenſion and followed with the Impotence of the ſufferer: But that no degree of ſuccour whatſoever without reference to this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170303:18"/>can merit ſuch an Attribute.</p>
            <p>This <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue</hi> yet muſt farther be more purely qualified to attain her perfect luſtre, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <hi>Her</hi> Original really celéſtiall: <hi>Shee muſt not iſſue from any materiall conſideration, End or Relation what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever:</hi> what? not from the reflection of our own frailty, ſubject to like Accidents, might move us timely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for a delivery, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, or a generall Commiſeration: No,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170303:19"/>ſuch Intention wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on <hi>Her,</hi> producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were but oblique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to trace our <hi>vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Notion</hi> in a civill Policy: What? not the conſideration of anothers Virtue, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Honour, Dignity? No, that were to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute a Rule holds no conformity with the Pattern of <hi>Her</hi> perfect eſſence, who ſuffered onely for the ſafety of the vildeſt criminals. May then the glory of the Action inflame our wils to propagate <hi>Her</hi> beeing? No, that were
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170303:19"/>to proſtitute the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt virtue to the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the loweſt vice. May our Relations yet in Nature claim this priviledge. No, that were to admit the moſt ſenſuall and irrationall Beaſt to a Capacity of the divineſt excellence; ſince they, by inſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive motives do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually with us endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to preſerve their own Productions.</p>
            <p>Nay, we muſt yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſence of our <hi>Diſtinction</hi> farther to delineate <hi>Her</hi> Purity: concluding that <hi>Shee</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170303:20"/>proceeds in <hi>Her</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity <hi>againſt any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, End, or Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> might in humane ſenſe retract her Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: which ſhall want no other Authority for confirmation, than His Example and Precept enlightned our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the ſacred myſtery of Her Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who enjoyns our Miniſtry to them that hate us, to them that deſpitefully perſecute us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus briefly ſearched into the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Eſſence of this ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170303:20"/>virtue: we will endeavour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe under what mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Arguments our common frailty can ſo far diſguiſe pretended Piety, to challenge to our ſelves hereof the firſt Inherency: and how nigh vulgar Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice hath aſſumed Her ſimilitude, or yet <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> attained the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their own impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Notion. Tis true the order of Nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that we firſt <hi>be,</hi> before we can be uſeful unto others. But while we are, the order of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170303:21"/>this <hi>ſacred virtue</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time may exact, that our preſent beings ceaſe for the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of anothers; of which we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples even in civill Rules; <hi>Curtius, Scevola, Regulus.</hi> But when with the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhe ſhall yet take a higher flight: &amp; <hi>earneſtly deſire (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) to be ſecluded from eternall Glory, Peace, and Comfort, for his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ſake;</hi> What In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination ſo barbarous, that is not ſilenced with a ſtupendious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of Her Glory;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170303:21"/>Yet theſe Patterns (ſome may perhaps al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) to be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to our ſpeculation than our practiſe: nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er our admiration, than our Imitation: (what we deſire not to attain, we plead an Incapacity to effect) but if granted ſo; they are not here improperly inferr'd, when onely to confute <hi>this ſpecious texture,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the indulgence to our ſelves hath wrought, and lend the ſenſuall ſoul a clear intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, how far our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Tempers are from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170303:22"/>the attaining of her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence; when we ſo ſhallowly diſtinguiſh of her Eſſence: To which may poſſibly farther be objected, that we herein extend the ſence of this <hi>Her</hi> Character to a more ſpeciall and peculiar Influence of grace than falls within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſpenſation to humanity: or the due limmits of ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept might compoſe unto all a generall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, which reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but <hi>to love our neigh bour as our ſelves;</hi> not to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170303:22"/>fer their Intereſts to our own. Tis true ſuch is the litterall ſence of this equilibrate Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſigured to us by that ſacred <hi>Light,</hi> who formed <hi>Her</hi> proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as framed onely to the fraile capacity of our common uſage: But not that either the excellence of <hi>Her</hi> luſtre, or the extent of our Devoir ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of ſo ſenſuall a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineation: Being here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in included (as in other Precepts) a ſpirituall ſence to inanimate the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170303:23"/>Letter; not diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhable to a ſenſuall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection: ſuch was the expanſion of that vail'd Light, revealed to us in the Expoſition of the Law; by that celeſtial guide, who only could fulfill the ſame; <hi>It is ſaid, Thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery; But I ſay, whoſoever ſeeth a woman and luſteth after her hath already committed Adultery with her in his heart.</hi> Nor doth the implicite ſenſe of the former Injunction diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Eclareiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the latter:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170303:23"/>When brought unto the Teſt; by him that would uphold he had obſerv'd them from his Infancy, to the ſequell of the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being annexed this ſupplement; <hi>Sell All thou haſt, and give it to the Poore: All,</hi> is ſo far from admitting of a Partner in this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Miniſtry, that it implies not ſo much, as a participation even to our property: Our proper Intereſts here being totally ejected forth the ballance of the former Rule in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170303:24"/>competition with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Miſery: ſome may perhaps except againſt the Collation of this Parrallel, as not altogether competent to form a generall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, in that the Party inſtanc'd was a ſingle Perſon, without any dependance on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or other on him: either of which might probably ſeem of force to alter the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo ſtrict an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: Since <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſors of their family are in the ballance of Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but counterpoiſed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170303:24"/>with unbelievers.</hi> A ſpecious evaſion to ſhroud affected Avarice from the Capacity of ſo requiſite a Miniſtry: and in the extent of ſuch poſition, yeelds almoſt every member of the ſame a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of omiſſion, mans Avarice or Ambition, Vanity or Lux in any one condition whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever not poſſibly meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch preſcription might move him wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to turn the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of his Aſſluence from his proper Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts or Pleaſures. Moſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170303:25"/>pretending the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, induceth them to the Enlargement of their Revenues: but where the due propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch bounds ſhould terminate are indiſcoverable to the proper mover: for the nigher they ſeem to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Object, the more remote are they from the attaining it: new acquiſitions beget new deſires', and new deſires new acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; ſo that it may be admitted a civill poſition as well as a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170303:25"/>Math'maticall conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: That the whole ſublunary Orbe cannot in the application, fill the extending angles of man's ſtil vacant heart: if it ſhall be required, where then may termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the due bounds of mans irregular deſires. It may be anſwered, that in Naturall Rules, what is, <hi>ultra Neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi> is ſuperfluous, if not deſtructive; what is <hi>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Decentiam,</hi> is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; if not ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: As in the moſt perfect conſtitution of Naturall compoſitions:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170303:26"/>ſo in the moſt regular form of civill Textures, there will be few found ſo low or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent; which may not fall under this preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption; there being in moſt Temperatures and Fortunes, either <hi>multa Superflua,</hi> or <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Aliena, many things Superſiuous, or many Strange.</hi> From which concluſion may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ariſe a ſcruple, What then ſhould be the Encouragement or Fruits of humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry? If all the toyl thereof ſhould meet no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170303:26"/>other end, than the bare ſupport of her proper Fabrique? Why? (without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to our future condition.) Is it not a higher merit, dignity, ſatisfaction, to ſecure anothers beeing, than to lend uſeleſſe diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements to our own? Can there be a more juſt acquiſition of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, A thore plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Echo to our Fame, A more firm band to our Amity. Such cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly was his Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſe Adviſe did direct our faculties
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170303:27"/>to this Object: <hi>Labour with thy hands to be helpfull unto others.</hi> Nor muſt it be the Refuge of our Acquiſition, that were an ungracefull loan to offer unto the Almighty; ſince he for ſuch vouchſafes to own it: <hi>Who giveth to the Poore, lendeth to God.</hi> But <hi>ex Primitiis, of the firſt,</hi> and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fruits thereof, ſuch were the Qualifications even of the Heathen Offerings to their illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Deities. But the Uſage of our times, (though inſtiled with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170303:27"/>the glorious Attribute of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> (The whole ſtructure of which Profeſſion, but raiſed on the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Practice) will in our moſt zealous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations ſcarce reach to the Excreſcence of our incumbring ſtore: which may ſigurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaid, but the ſnip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of our hair, or the pairings of our nails; rather Illuſtrations to our civill Fame, than progreſſions to our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture felicity, badges ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our vanity, than production of our Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170303:28"/>ſo far are we from ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crificing onevice in this oblation, that we make even vice it ſelf the Object of our offering. How then can our vices here by meet a pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which ſincerely preferd might effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>cover a multitude of tranſgreſſions.</hi> But our corrupt Inclinations are ſo far from adher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the viſible traces of this <hi>virtue</hi> (which flies in her cordial Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, not onely the ſeeming approaches of anothers diſcovery: but even of her own ſecret
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170303:28"/>Teſtimony, <hi>not letting one hand know what the other doth.</hi>) That we ſound thereto a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet in the moſt affluent Conventions: raiſe proud ſtructures with Inſcriptions thereof, to keep our Glory in the memory of Poſterity: &amp; when all this? when our frailty hath left us no longer faculties to reliſh hereof the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements, or to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of thoſe boaſting Reliques. O ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſtupidity! Shall not the Indian Heathen (as we preſume to call
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170303:29"/>them) in their clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to impotent Fowle and Beaſt (without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of merit, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding publique Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles for their Relief) riſe up in judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. But if we think Divine Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons too heavy a burden for our frailty: let us examine how far the force onely of Civill rules may really herein extend themſelves. <hi>Non nobis naſcimur, we are not born for our ſelves.</hi> According to the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of this Principle; we are ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170303:29"/>the firſt Object of our own proper En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, that in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſe and end thereof, we are not ſo much as admitted to a partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation in the intention of our primitive pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction: So neceſſary is the Communication of our faculties, to the due ſupport of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Fabrique. From whence we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude both in the Civil and the Natural frame. <hi>Pars ſibi tantùm vivens jam morti proxima eſt; That part which liveth onely to it ſelf, is already
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170303:30"/>on the conſines of Death.</hi> Such a priviledge, nor the greateſt, nor the meaneſt can aſſume un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves, without deſtruction to their proper beeing. <hi>Et cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Dignitas conſiſtit tantùm in commodo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius; And the dignity of each part conſiſteth onely in the benefit ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thereby receiveth:</hi> Nor is the extent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of limited within the circumſcription of a private Family, Name, Nation, Sect or Faction: <hi>ſed to to humano generi;</hi> But <hi>to all mankinde: at
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170303:30"/>quò remotius ſubjectum, eò Nobilius effectum,</hi> And <hi>How much more remote the ſubject; So much more noble the thing ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. Alienis &amp; inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Adminiſtrare, eſt ſibi proprium commodum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare.</hi> To adminiſter to ſtrangers and enemies, is truly to deny unto our ſelves our proper intereſts. <hi>Solomon</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the ſenſe thereof yet farther, affirming, <hi>(A good man to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to his Beaſt.)</hi> The happy effects of which communicative <hi>virtue</hi> may be viſibly manifeſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170303:31"/>to every common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, ſhall conſider how thoſe Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths have attained the higheſt felicity of a perfect Government, that in their forms of common union have repreſented but one ſingle family, as the <hi>Spartans</hi> among the <hi>Greeks;</hi> the <hi>Eſſeans</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews.</hi> Their proviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s iſſuing equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the common care and Induſtry; the Elevation. Education, and Inſtruction of their youth, of all earneſtly proſecuted as one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170303:31"/>Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Having thus in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Charity,</hi> diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed how far our own primary Inherence may become conſiſtent with divine or civill Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: our premiſed order requires, we ſhould next preſent a Form hereof, produced from the vulgar uſage; that by a due collation of their Patterns, we may more viſibly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh of the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their Natures.</p>
            <p>In Order to which, we will in general, firſt, ſeverally reflect on the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170303:32"/>Eſſentiall parts of our mutuall community and commerce; though through the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Nature, they ſeldome are divided in the Practice; the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer being frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but a diſguiſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction to the Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>The ſimple Objects of an unimpeachable community, are, <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatio, congratulatio, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio &amp; conſolatio.</hi> Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation, Congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Solace, and Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subjects moſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170303:32"/>properly inherent to the firſt uſage, <hi>is gratum aliquid facere, agnoſcere vel reſtituere.</hi> To ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, acknowledge, or requite a benefit. The firſt two Branches of this diſtinction are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frequent, motives in vulgar practice to civil Addreſſes: and the latter not altogether unuſuall: (But accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the intention) neither the one nor the other falleth under the due limits of a ſimple and unimpeachable community; ſince they are but artificiall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170303:33"/>to future and more advantageous pretences: ſo that ſuch forms of intercourſe may more properly be termed a traffique for Lucre, than a tender of Beneficence or Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which onely meets the perfect Teſt, when as ſome preſſing Exigent invites a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuccour: But ſuch extreams, like falling Fabricks, affright them fartheſt from it have had moſt ſhelter by it. No relation whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will hazzard any Intereſt to ſupport
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170303:33"/>where the ſucceſſe to humane ſence appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth doubtfull. In op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive every one can form unto himſelf a ſubtle caution. <hi>Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt meipſum ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiare nemini grato.</hi> It ſeeming an abſurd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure to ingratiate our ſelves to him is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come acceptable to none. In ſuch deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents unnaturally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon their Children, and the Children as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiouſly neglect their Parents: Thoſe ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170303:34"/>purſue theſe in their fall, with Rebukes. Theſe irreverently, thoſe with Revilings: Brothers will rather ſtrain their credite to ſupplant each other in their Poſſeſſions, than to ſupply each other to preſerve them. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults are onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull in their ill ſucceſſe; but who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth not, if not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaudes the underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of a proſperous miſcheif. Be the actions and intentions clearly free from any reference to the unhappy iſſue;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170303:34"/>yet miſery ſhall ſeldom meet in the officious viſits of the nigheſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; but an inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting reproach: <hi>And where the Almighty God ſhall pleaſe to lay his hand, Inſolent man will preſume to ſet his foot.</hi> In Repugnance to the latter Motive (which in ſtrictneſſe of civill Rules may ſometime poſſibly meet in one center where the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city not anſwereth the Will, man thinks it an imputation to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour publiquely to profeſſe by a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170303:35"/>compenſation to have held Advantage from a thing ſo mean, could fall to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in civill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; and had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther elate his vanity in ſome magnificent preſent, or entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than remunerate a benefit in a gracefull Retribution. The high endearments of the choiceſt amity, richeſt preſents, moſt ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous extertainments, ſhall in the adverſe ſtate ſcarcely produce a Recompence meet for the grooms that uſherd
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170303:35"/>them; who meeting in one Point of Fortune, are meaſured, by the ſame Rules in eſteem, Corrupt humanity! we have dayly proofs of gratitude twixt Fiſh, Fowle, and Beaſt of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall kindes, and of them all to man in his Extream, but of mans timely ayde to man in his adverſity, no tie could ere afford, or truth from Hiſtory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; witneſſe upright <hi>Jobs</hi> wofull viſitants, and ſhe, who in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluent proſperity had produc'd ſo many
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170303:36"/>faithfull pledges of her love in a flouriſhing fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility, could not in the bitter Agony of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction afford him one gentle word in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable miniſtry. And that vigorous and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely illuminated ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, who for his ſtable integrity, was deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to be the Rock, whereon the ſacred ſtructure of our ſaving Faith ſhould be erected could not, in his extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity unto his Saviour, (who had on him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd that dignity) ſo much allow as an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170303:36"/>Teſtimony.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond object of community, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulation,</hi> holds an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction from a more alluring ſubject, moſt men with alacrity ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering homage to a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing proſperity. But ſtill with reference to their proper Intereſts, a procedure moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in uſe 'mong eminent Perſonages, on the ſucceſſefull Iſſues of their enterpriſes, and may be judged rather an act of Ceremony, than an office of ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: though the inherent
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170303:37"/>Pretences and exterior conſequence thereof may ſeem to bear a more plauſible inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being uſually illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated with ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſents, ſpecious proffers, high Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſuch were the Ornaments to <hi>Jobs</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration from thoſe degenerate Relations, that in his dejected tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, under the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of friendſhip did but exaggerate his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery with reproch. And truly evident it is to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very common obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that ſuch obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quious
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170303:37"/>endearments are but ſecret Ambages to reſerved purpoſes. If otherwiſe theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiall Interludes, divided from ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are attended with diſguiſed emulation, envy or inemnity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The next enſuing object of community is <hi>ſolace,</hi> the moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent attractive and univerſal of all the reſt, man being naturally a ſociable and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative Creature, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing relaxes from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of his primitive
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170303:38"/>Infliction by ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals, as the burden neceſſary to his exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence will permit, if contemplative ſeeking agreeable iſſues to the digeſted Idea's of the minde, for the uſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, or inſtruction of anothers ſpirit, delight, confirmation or illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his own; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derthe limit of preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, may probably be figured a plauſible di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſment, proper and approvable to every Sex, Age or Function. The which particulars, though all or moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170303:38"/>to proſecute in the Election of Society; Yet few, or none, do once ſo much as figure to themſelves the Uſe, End, or the Propriety of this Object in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſeparated from Intereſt or Affair, is but followed to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſenſual appetite; to waſte our precious houres in a caſual, vain, impertinent babble, to make an Oſtentation of ſome ridiculous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentry, or ſport our ſelves with others deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The laſt Object
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170303:39"/>of an uninterreſſed community, is <hi>conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the onely true legitimate and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iſſue of this celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>virtue,</hi> having no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther motive, but onely the compaſſionate and effectuall ſenſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers miſery: of which there are two kindes, Speculative and Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall; The former with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the latter, may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſometime, in the agent, be inveſted with ſuch Impotence, as may not altogether dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the dignity of ſuch Original, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170303:39"/>alſo, in the different quality of the Miniſtry, appropriated wholy to the nature of the Paſſion; as in the Intellectual diſtempers, where the diſtracted ſpirit requires onely a rational preſcription to reſtore it to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer luſtre: yet uſually ſuch officious tenders are but a ſpurious, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall compliance 'twixt eminent Perſonages on ſome diſaſterous Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current: A Ceremony more frequently in practiſe in former ages, nor out of cuſtome ſtill
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170303:40"/>in the Eaſtern parts 'twixt nigh Relations. But ſuch a ſuperficiall Miniſtry to an exterior deſiciency, (where o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe indued with capacity) may rather be termed a ſhameleſſe and inſulting mockery, than ſo much as a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane civility: no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty being without grudging more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable than words, the ſum of all friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betwixt man and man; and of all profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion 'twixt man and God. The reall and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall being but an
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170303:40"/>imaginary point we fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in the ſphear of our diſcourſe, to finde the perfect elevation of <hi>this ſplendid Attribute,</hi> the ſenſual appearance thereof being inſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to our ſenſe in humane Society; as we may truly collect from the due perpenſation of our Argument; ſince we cannot therein diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſo much as the ſhadow of a debonary Indulgency to a diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed calamity to iſſue from any practical Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity. We ſhould
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170303:41"/>next proceed to agitate on the more uſuall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluent and univerſall object of humane en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe prepoſited in the inception of our Texture; <hi>Commerce,</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon receptacle to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> premis'd occurences, as the Ocean to the Rivu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets. But in the inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch tranſaction, we have yet leſſe hope to diſcover what we are in ſearch of (the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of this divine <hi>Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute;</hi> than in the preme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned particulars: and in the attempt, purſue a fruitleſſe enterpriſe:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170303:41"/>ſince it is manifeſt to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very common ſenſe, without a farther cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, that mans Infirmity or Neceſſity, the onely true Objects of <hi>Charity,</hi> do but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in yeeld him up to be the fitter prey to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Lucre: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a civill Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce might poſſibly meet a juſt preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yet is it ſo rare and difficult a procedure, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>wiſeman</hi> affirms the Agitators herein, can hardly keep their hands clean. In which reſpect, they were but
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170303:42"/>as Thieves, reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſecluded from the common receit of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Convention: Nor are the forms of Negotiation in the weighteſt or the ſleigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt tranſaction, mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with leſſe furbery, circumvention and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, even to the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a common viſit; ſo vilde and corrupt an Impoſturie attendeth on humane coherency: that even the moſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious gloſſes of his cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie are but a ſubtle traffick of propriety: Yet that inſulting cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170303:42"/>may not ſo far corrupt the judgment, as to deprive us of the uſe of Reaſon in civill practiſes, under a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall preſcription: no man making ſcruple to act, what is in general uſage licenc'd by the Authority of the Law; we will proceed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance farther, wherein ſuch legall forms are not only repugnant to <hi>Charity,</hi> but to Equity and Humanity; nor can ſuch Ordinance be a ſufficient warrant to a rationall mans inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity; who ought ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170303:43"/>to ſeparate the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of his actions from any ineſſentiall circumſtances &amp; forms, under what dignity ſo ere authorized; to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert ſome inſtances hereof, leaſt it might altogether appear an empty ſuggeſtion. An induſtrious acquiſitor becomes plauſibly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of a reall Eſtate: and although the end of his endeavour labor and care, was but to ſupport his numerous iſ2ue of either ſex: (for the Law of God, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Nations allow
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170303:43"/>not of any diſtinction between them) yet Death, by caſualty ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing him, ſhall by the Authority of the Law, fruſtrate this his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conferring the ſucceſsion to his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, onely on the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenitor; who ſhall with as much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence enjoy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thereof without reflection on the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of his Fathers naked members; as if his affluent Revenues were but the fruits of his own proper Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. Oh! barbarous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herency!
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170303:44"/>But much more brutiſh, where ſuch eſtates are ſo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily conſtituted by the voluntary vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the acquiſition, for what right of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief can be pleaded for their ſuccour from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily abandoned by their own naturall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. Oh, the glory of a Name! Oh, ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſhame! Can a man with Honour or Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſet a Diadem on his Head, and leave the reſt of his Members na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked or tatter'd. Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170303:44"/>paſſion for a dirty fame: Tis virtue onely can be a perfect Ornament to a family, not Pow'r, not Wealth, not Dignity; ſince ſuch ineſſentiall ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of renown vaniſh even in their firſt eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, like an empty noiſe. The right ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors to the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Monark of the world, in a ſmall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time, became but poor enſlaved Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caniques at <hi>Rome.</hi> But to omit farther Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of this inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170303:45"/>cuſtome: admit the ſplendid Title might ſupport this gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Pagentry ſhould faile; even in the firſt ſucceſſion, the generall iſſue of the Poſſeſſor ſhall totally exclude the general iſſue of the Acquiſitor from any Intereſt of Inheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. A pretty piece of legal Sophiſtry. In ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which caſes was never yet heard of any, that brooked the fruition of ſuch privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which ſo much ſcruple of erroneous partiality, as might ſupport the equal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170303:45"/>from ſtarving, though the unequit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Advantages were ne're ſo affluent: ſo willing are the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved inclinations of brutiſh man to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh in their ſecret Conſciences, the lights of Nature or of Grace, in favour of their Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, or ſenſuality, when the adulterate gloſſes of the Law may lend an influence to ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure. Nay, ſuch is the tyranny of inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting cuſtome, over ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile ſpirits, that where no viſible advantages ſucceed the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170303:46"/>of the unequall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Law: Yet the barbarous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity of man, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſcruple of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, ſubmits to the formalities thereof, though to the unjuſt extinction of anothers life: as in matters of <hi>Petty Larcin.</hi> A moſt exquiſite encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to common Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where the light of civill commerce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes an inſtigator to inhumane Practiſes.</p>
            <p>Having ſo far as our frailty will permit, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to diſcover
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170303:46"/>the glorious Graces of that celeſtiall and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material <hi>light</hi> did firſt give influence to our Treatiſe: as alſo weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how far the reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her <hi>luſtre</hi> may, in vulgar Practice, agree with the true Nature of her Eſſence. It now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth onely for clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our Texture, to examine how far, <hi>this Vulgar Poſition,</hi> may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reach the Inference therein included.</p>
            <p>In order whereto we may infer, that ſuch ſelf Indulgence <hi>therein</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed viſibly tendeth
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170303:47"/>onely <hi>fovere genio, to cheriſh</hi> the ſenſuall <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination,</hi> and can have no other Object than Ambition, Vanity, Lux or Avarice. Now how any of theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſeverally or joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may tend to the compoſure of mans preſent felicity, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reference to his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condition, to the Improvement whereof they ſolely are inque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable obſtacles) we will proceed to figure.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Ambition, the higheſt paſſion of the minde, to which (when
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170303:47"/>her Rights are in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) all others ſtill give place: can to it ſelf propound no other Good, but the ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of anothers actions to the preſcription of our will. If ſuch inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Arrogance ſhall (through an affected ſufficiency) pretend the end of their ſupremacy is but aſſumed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſtubborn tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the unformd multitude to civill or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; we may thereto object, that a modeſt Reaſon onely ſhould preſide the motions of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170303:48"/>anothers ſpirit, to lend it a more regular Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, deveſted from the very appearance of violence or peculiar intereſts, which always are the onely uſhers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced and columns that ſupport this high Prerogative: Or were ſuch terrible inveſtures warrantable to ſhrowd the juſt Pretenders from thoſe fatall iſſues do commonly attend the undertakings of a naked Inſtitutor, though ſupernaturally inſpired, yet what af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity, ſimiltude or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170303:48"/>can there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the quality of the means, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the intention: between the regulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the minde, and the deſtruction of the Body; or if admitted for allowable, Can rationall man be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagantly poſſeſſed with paſsion for anothers diſagreeing benefit, as to waide through ſo many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, guilty, coſtly, penible Tracts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct to this ſupremacy, without a reference to ſatisfie our own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170303:49"/>which alſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weighed in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and purſuit, fruit and fruition are but ineſſentially pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; the Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſtil attended with violation of Rights, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, Naturall and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine: The conſequence upheld with ſlaughters devaſtation, oppreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the cries and tears of deſolate widdows, the mourning and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of innocent Orphans; the fruit aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociated exteriourly with the inſeparable Furies, Envie and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170303:49"/>interriourly with that of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inappeaſable and ſecret horrour of his own guilt: the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition uncertain, the iſſue tragicall, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of parts, in the Nature of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects muſt queſtionleſſe produce a prepoſterous Harmony to form the life of man agreeable. Vanity is but the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard Brother to the former diſtemper of the Minde: poſsibly contended with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour ſhaddow of ſuch immenſitie, <hi>glory,</hi> and empty rumour
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170303:50"/>from an empty Vaut, popular applauſe. A mercenary Idolatry de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to it ſelf: a chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging gale to every Sale.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Lux, pretends to a more material Object of delight, in adulation to the ſenſe; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the intent of her ſollicitous Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to ſatisfie, ſatiates in ſtead of ſuccouring, to ſupply clogs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy: whilſt oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Nature ſinking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burden of a prepoſterous Miniſtry, contracts more painful and laſting Infirmities
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170303:50"/>than could be threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by her Indigence.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Avarice, the vild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, vaineſt, and prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous affection can taint the Reaſon or poſſeſſe the Spirit, vild, in that it indirectly purſues the baſeſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the prejudice or deſtruction of another; vain, in that the more it advanceth in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the means, the farther it is diſtant from attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the End. Prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in that man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes himſelf in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of his own ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170303:51"/>yet attaining the materials thereto, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies himſelf the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition thereof, He maketh no ſcruple of any crime to encreaſe his uſeleſſe ſtore, that another may enjoy the fruit of his Vice; who though the nigheſt Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of his loins, wiſheth if not procureth his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: and be his prudence ne're ſo cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in the equall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, ſhall at his Obſequies, be only gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with opprobrious reproaches, ſlanderous
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170303:51"/>murmurs, ſecret ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrations of his proper blood. So that we may conclude from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of our Diſcourſe in reference to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, if juſtly ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; That ſuch <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as begins at home,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ends there: and never extends farther. And who directs his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions by this <hi>preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Eſt homini lupus, ſibi ipſi Diabolus; is to others a Woolf, to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Devill;</hi> from which obſervation, hath queſtionleſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded this proverbiall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170303:52"/>Imprecation, <hi>Dieu me guarde de moy: God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me from my ſelf:</hi> which may poſſibly, at firſt Inſpection appear a groſs Impropriety; in that it might be thought, no rationall man will prejudice himſelf: yet when we ſhall reflect, how mans extravagant indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to his ſenſuall inclinations doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the glorious I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, ſhould illuſtrate his Nature with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence. We may without all contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction affirm the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170303:52"/>That no pow'r Humane or Diabolicall can in any thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice man, but himſelf or by himſelf. It may therefore without far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extention of this Treatiſe, become evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to every common ſenſe, That the Nature of ſuch <hi>Charity.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in our Vulgar Poſition, is ſo far from any reall affinity with this <hi>Celeſtiall Virtue,</hi> whereof it would aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Figure, that it can no way imply this primary Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170303:53"/>Adulterately ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed in <hi>the ſpecious Texture.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170303:53"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 10. l. <hi>ult.</hi> r. <hi>Act,</hi> p 18. l. 12. r <hi>Exterior co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,</hi> p. 29. l 5. r. <hi>Texture,</hi> p. 60. l. 13 r. <hi>which preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi> p 72. l. 6. r. <hi>Acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> p. 83. l. <hi>ult.</hi> r. <hi>an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
